[Music]
an integer partition of an integer n is
a list of integers l1 l2 up to lk
satisfying the properties that n is the
sum of the integers in the list and the
integers in the list are weakly
decreasing and greater than or equal to
1. the elements in the list are called
parts
for example the list 43211 is an integer
partition of eleven because eleven is
equal to four plus three plus two plus
one plus one this is a partition of
eleven into five parts
the young diagram of a partition is an
array of boxes with li boxes in row i
so for example the young diagram of the
partition 43211 is pictured here because
there are four boxes in the first row
then three then two then one and then
one
let's let p of n be the number of
integer partitions of n and p sub k of n
be the number of integer partitions of n
with k parts
if we're trying to compute p of n we can
list out all of the young diagrams for n
in this case we have n is nine and here
are all the partitions
natural way to organize the partitions
is to group them together with other
partitions with the same number of parts
as we've done here
[Music]
the smallest number of parts a partition
can have is one and the largest number
of parts it can have is n where each
part has size one this visual shows us
that the number of partitions of n is
equal to the sum of the number of
partitions of n into k parts where k
ranges from 1 to n
now we can present our primary result
about the number of partitions of n into
k parts
if we have all the partitions of n into
k parts we can divide these into two
disjoint sets the first set are the
partitions that have a part of size one
and the second set consists of the
partitions with no part of size one the
partitions that have a part of size one
are in one-to-one correspondence with
those partitions where we remove one of
the parts of size one
but these partitions are just the
partitions of n minus one into k minus
one parts so we can count them using p
sub k minus one of n minus one for each
of the partitions that have no part of
size one we can remove one from each
part resulting in a partition of n minus
k into k parts these can be counted by p
sub k of n minus k both of these
processes are reversible and because the
two sets have no elements in common we
see that p sub k of n is equal to p sub
k minus one of n minus one plus p sub k
of n minus k
this is a recursive formula for p sub k
of n the number of partitions of n into
k parts we now see that we do not need
to enumerate all of the partitions to
know how many there are
instead we can use the two formulas that
we just encountered to find the number
of partitions of size n
namely we can realize that the number of
partitions of n is equal to the sum of
the number of partitions of n into k
parts where k ranges from one to n and
that the number of partitions of n into
k parts satisfies the recursion given
here
of course this is only one such
technique to count the number of
partitions of n can you think of a
different way to count them
you